From the beginning, humans have looked
at the natural world and wondered,
"Where did this come from?
Why are we here? And how can we solve
the great mysteries,
find the hidden secrets?"
And as we began to build, those ideas
were embedded in our structures, from
the Stone Age
to the Modern Age.
The churches, synagogues, mosques, and
temples we see today were built with a
secret code of sorts.
Unlocking that code can tell us a great
deal about our quest for things above
and our passions here on Earth.
In the 19th century, the people who
owned the railroads became fabulously
rich.
One of those moguls was William Banning
of St. Paul, Minnesota.
He served in the state legislature and
accumulated enormous wealth.
In 1914,
the Banning family funded one of the
most spectacular stained glass windows
in the country.
But there is a hidden secret in this
window that's been lost to history until
it was recently rediscovered.
One of the Bible figures looked exactly
like William Banning.
>> There's a man looking down and it looks
exactly like the picture in the
Minnesota Historical Society.
>> The image is so high up, it can't be
clearly seen with the naked eye. But,
once the first likeness was rediscovered
in 2013,
several more were soon identified,
including Banning's wife, Mary,
their son, William,
and a mysterious, still unidentified
bearded man.
It was not uncommon in the 19th century
to depict major church donors in stained
glass windows.
It was an arrangement that brought
building funds to churches and a lasting
legacy to donors.
>> So, they might not be able to see it,
but they might know exactly where it is,
and then they've been part of that group
that's put their stamp on that building
that's,
you know, present in that building
forever.
>> Most of these secret images have been
forgotten for more than a century, but
they remain tucked away in stained glass
all over the country.
Like so many architectural features,
they're just waiting to be rediscovered.
The burning of Notre Dame was a stark
reminder of the irreplaceable value of
the great medieval churches, all built
in a unique style we now call Gothic.
>> You know, it's stone. It's not going
anywhere. It's carved stone.
>> To give that feeling of permanence.
>> The hallmark feature of Gothic design is
the pointed arch, a structural
innovation that allowed churches to soar
higher and higher with larger and larger
windows
filled with colored glass.
>> You walk in and it's the ceiling soar
and you just feel like you can fly.
>> And then when you fill it up with smoke
from the incense burning devices and it
becomes this fantastic late afternoon
light and they're chanting in front of
you in Latin, it's this mysterious
language that's going on and they're
dressed in these beautiful vestments and
there's lots of gold and there's lots of
color and oh my goodness, you are in
another world.
>> Gothic design reached its apex with
Chartres Cathedral built in France more
than 800 years ago.
In an era when a tall building might be
three stories high, Chartres towered 35
stories into the sky.
>> The discovery of the power of the
pointed arch and then the buttressing
system, I mean, it was really quite
phenomenal what those engineers
produced.
>> Gothic is one of those times when
architects stepped out of the known
way of making things
into a new territory.
>> But then, Gothic architecture fell out
of favor abandoned by builders
for centuries.
It wasn't until the 1800s that Gothic
design was rediscovered and then quickly
became the single most popular template
for new church buildings in America.
Why the revival?
Part of the reason
is this.
Mary Shelley's book Frankenstein was
part of a larger movement to reconnect
with the mystery of the Middle Ages.
>> It's all about emotion. It's all about,
you know, fear, love, hate, right? It's
and Mary Shelley is part of that.
>> As authors, musicians, and artists
rediscovered the Gothic period,
architects followed suit, creating new
churches that evoked the awe and mystery
of the medieval age,
a style that came to be called Gothic
Revival.
>> By the time you reach the 19th century,
certain people are looking back at
Gothic and saying, "Oh, this actually
was a style that had important meaning."
>> Anyone who steps into a Gothic Revival
church today can immediately sense that
the intent is to transport church goers
to an earlier time and place, an
idealized era when it seemed that all
great architecture
was church architecture.
>> When people thought about Gothic
architecture,
you thought about it was a sacred space.
And so, people were willing to bring it
back.
>> The soaring heights, massive stone, and
especially the dancing colored light
make an emotional connection.
>> And so, the quality of the space changes
based on the interaction of color in the
glass
with color that's coming just from the
sky at a particular time of day.
The natural light in a church building
reminds us
that we are
beings that exist
on a journey that's spiritual,
but we exist in an environment that is
temporal and changing and moving
in time.
>> In recent years, scientists have
rediscovered secrets about natural light
that Gothic builders knew intuitively a
thousand years ago.
Namely, that daylight has profound
effects on the human psyche, boosting
attentiveness and creating a sense of
well-being.
>> Studies now have shown
when there is daylight as opposed to
artificial light,
test scores are better. We learn better
in natural light.
There's a reason that retailers like
Walmart have put
skylights in all of their buildings. An
expensive endeavor,
but what they found out is people feel
better
when they're connected to the natural
environment as opposed to completely
dependent on artificial light.
>> Among the best known of America's Gothic
Revival churches is the Washington
National Cathedral.
>> Great Gothic Revival building, built
actually with Gothic techniques of no
prefabrication and no steel in that
thing.
>> The idea of a national church in the US
capital dates back to George Washington,
but the first stones were not laid until
1907.
And the building wasn't completed until
1990.
The process took so long that some
decisions made early on were not the
same choices Americans would make today.
>> We're a country supposedly founded on
plural religious expression.
Why would you think that it would ever
be appropriate in that context to have
one church that represents everybody,
especially cuz it's a church, and not
everybody worships in a church?
>> Despite its Protestant pedigree, the
Washington National Cathedral welcomes
people of all faiths
and even connects visitors to secular
icons as seen in the church's most
curious artifact, a gargoyle styled to
look like Darth Vader.
>> You know, they promote that like crazy.
And then of course there's a stained
glass window in there to the Apollo moon
missions with a piece of moon rock in
it.
>> The National Cathedral's massive
grandeur is one way Americans express
their faith through Gothic architecture.
At the other end of the spectrum are
small wooden churches that populate much
of the snowy northern tier of states.
Many built in a style called carpenter
Gothic.
>> They couldn't be simpler. Just a little
box with a pitched roof on top and some
two by fours on the outside. Nothing
complicated about it, but beautiful.
>> These simple churches may not get the
attention of grand cathedrals,
but they reflect the modest lifestyles
of rural America.
>> Churches tended to use what they had
readily available.
I'm always amazed, however, at what
churches were able to do with timber.
The community builds it, right? They are
functional
and they are gorgeous. They're simple
rectangular solids. They're basically a
version of the same building type that a
cathedral is, just made out of wood and
smaller.
>> Even small churches retain little hints
of a bigger history, like the Gothic
pointed arch shape that connects these
buildings to a tradition dating back
millennia.
The medieval Gothic period it the only
inspiration for American architects.
Some looked back even further, getting
inspiration from ancient Rome.
In the late 1800s, dark storms of social
unrest were increasing.
Churches felt threatened by growing
atheism.
The response was an architectural style
called Romanesque.
These were churches that were hunkering
down and readying for a fight.
The design was fortress-like, with rough
stone and turret-style towers.
The windows were small, rounded arches
characteristic of battle-hardened
ancient Rome, not the delicate soaring
glass of the latter medieval period.
>> And they were understood as a vigorous,
masculine
type of activity.
>> These types of buildings were making a
statement that Christianity is here and
it's massive and it's going to stay here
for a long time.
>> At the same time, other churches wanted
to project a very different message, a
connection to the logic, reason, and
democracy of the ancient Greeks.
Churches built in this style, called
Greek Revival, looked like they'd be at
home in ancient Athens and make a
statement about the congregation's
connection to certain timeless values.
>> There's a formality to those kinds of
architectures, to Greek architecture,
that translates nicely to church. And
so, to have these solid, regular
architectures that we know, we know
they're historical, we know they tie to
something before us.
>> Christians were not the only groups
building places of worship that echoed
an earlier time.
This building, for example, might appear
Arabian, but it's actually a Jewish
synagogue in Cincinnati built in the
mid-1800s.
The design reflects a look from 400
years earlier in Islamic Spain during a
rare period when Jews were free to
practice their religion.
The style, called Moorish Revival, was a
popular choice for American synagogues.
>> And so you had Jews and Christians
living with Muslim leaders all in the
same place, and they all got along.
And so there are a surprising number of
synagogues that are built in the 19th
century that reflect this Moorish
period.
>> In the early 20th century, interest in
reviving old forms of architecture began
to wane.
There was a desire to start fresh, a
movement that came to be called
modernism.
>> The modernists are freed by the use of
materials and by the the tremendous
roiling change in culture
in general to look all around them and
ask the question, why does something
have to be the way it is just because it
was that before?
>> This new generation of architects
stripped away everything that came
before, rejecting thousands of years of
traditional design.
For many churchgoers, the result was
shocking.
>> So the minimization of decoration and
ornament and these forms that were
rectilinear and simple and
they were hard for some people to wrap
their heads around, that's for sure.
>> One famous example is the Air Force
Academy Chapel in Colorado.
Designed by architect Walter Netsch, it
hints at older styles with elements like
colored glass.
But it's also distinctly modern.
>> This is Walter Natches, very very smart
and challenging architect trying to
create multiple readings, multiple
possible readings on behalf of the
people using it.
>> People can draw different things from
art or architecture. It does look like
fighter jets shooting up into the air.
However, um in my conversation with
Walter Natches directly, uh he did tell
me that he designed it to pointing
straight up towards the heavens.
>> Is it beautiful? Oh my goodness, yes. Is
it a snowflake in the Rocky Mountains?
Is it a piece of the Rocky Mountains? A
chunk of ice that broke off and settled
down on the hill? It's all of those
things and it's more.
>> Unlike most sacred spaces, this building
needed to serve a range of faiths
present at the Academy.
Natches' solution to build separate
spaces for each religion
remains controversial.
>> The big beautiful part on top is for
Protestants.
And then there's a floor, and then
there's two more
uh big worship spaces, a a a fairly
large one for Catholics and a relatively
small one for Jews, right? They're
actually under the floor of the
Protestants.
>> So you can imagine that some of those
faiths look at that and interpret it as
an Huh.
Okay, then.
This must be a Protestant country. Is
that what you're trying to tell us?
>> The best known practitioner of
boundary-pushing modernism in church
architecture was Frank Lloyd Wright.
>> Frank Lloyd Wright looking at the world
and saying
if I'm going to build a church,
it's going to look American. I'm going
to build it out of out of materials that
are American. I'm going to
build it with an expression that is
rooted in this place.
>> An example of Wright's unique
perspective is visible here at
Annunciation Greek Orthodox Church,
which Wright imagined as a dome on top
of a bowl.
The bowl representing God's hands
holding the congregation.
The church can seat 800, yet the
circular design means no churchgoer is
more than 60 ft from the altar.
Reflecting an American view of
egalitarianism.
>> He completely wants the user to rethink
how they engage with buildings.
>> In a remarkable innovation, the dome is
not even attached to the rest of the
building and instead floats on a channel
of ball bearings to allow for expansion
and contraction throughout the seasons.
With a strong enough push, the entire
roof could spin like a top.
>> This man was radical.
Quite radical. Um, as an architect and
as a as a person the way he lived his
life, people never quite came to terms
with it.
>> Wright's design for Annunciation was
inspired by the 6th century Hagia Sophia
in Istanbul.
But Wright never copied older forms.
Instead, he used them as a launching pad
to create something entirely new.
>> He was doing something new. He wanted
architecture of an American spirit. He
didn't want these historical trappings.
>> As with many of Wright's
boundary-pushing ideas, the innovative
poured concrete dome was a challenge to
maintain. Interior insulation began to
peel away raining asbestos onto the pews
and tiles on the roof began to pop off
by the thousands.
Wright always considered these kinds of
issues with his buildings as irrelevant
because he was creating timeless works
of art.
>> When you know right, you know right
always kind of thought he knew
everything he was doing, right?
>> Despite his reputation for ego, church
leaders at Annunciation found right to
be friendly and accommodating to their
requests during the design phase.
And that positive relationship never
soured because right passed away in 1959
before construction even began.
The passing of Frank Lloyd Wright
coincided with the birth of a new era in
American sacred design.
As Hindu, Muslim, and Buddhist
populations in the United States grew to
the point where significant building
projects were feasible in the 1950s,
'60s, and '70s.
>> And when they came, they brought their
ideas of what faith meant to them.
>> We know in the North American context um
and especially the United States that
there are barriers for immigrant
communities to kind of make their way.
So, it takes longer.
>> Mosques, especially, have faced
resistance in many communities resulting
in designs that try not to draw
attention.
It's only been in recent decades that
Islamic architecture in America has
become more bold in emphasizing
traditional elements like minarets and
domes.
>> Islam, I have to say that they're
they're burdened by Islamophobia in our,
you know, cultural context in general.
>> And as you get more established as a
community, you can begin to express
yourself and the Muslim community has
begun to be able to express itself in
this country.
>> For marginalized groups, whether Muslim,
Hindu, or Christian, the local church
building is often the only gathering
place that's free from prejudice.
>> Oh, He's being
surrounded.
>> In the African-American community, that
was a place where we could go
to be our full selves.
>> That was a place where you had black
leadership.
>> That was the building we built.
And we could take credit for it. We
built other buildings, but this is the
one that we could say was ours.
>> As people of color congregated in city
centers,
wealthier suburbanites have kindled an
entirely new kind of religious
architecture that emerged in the 1980s.
You're seeing an example of one of the
most radical changes in church
architecture ever.
The megachurch.
All are echoing a template of trying to
look un-church-like.
>> Some of that expression of architecture
in its simplicity is sending a clear
message that this church is different.
>> The idea is to make everyone, especially
newcomers, feel welcome.
The traditional elements that signify a
church setting have been removed, so
there is no stained glass, no ornate
woodwork, and no steeple.
>> So, the church has to reach out and work
to explain why they are relevant
and why people might want to come into
their building.
>> These facilities bear a striking
resemblance to a shopping mall or office
park, and that's intentional because the
architecture of American business is
familiar and comfortable.
These churches have plenty of parking,
clear signage,
a coffee shop,
and plenty of space for gathering and
recreation.
While it might seem unusual for a church
to have athletic facilities, it's not
completely unprecedented. Congregations
have long considered recreation and
community gathering to be central to
their purpose.
>> Bowling alleys in the 1890s were really
popular in Protestant churches.
Basketball, of course, was invented
by
Protestants as a as a game to keep
particularly young men and boys off the
streets.
>> Megachurches today extend this
informality into the worship service
itself, reflecting a theology that sees
God as approachable, friendly.
It's a stark contrast to the gothic
design that emphasizes a God who is
awe-inspiring and all-powerful.
Most believers would say God can be all
those things,
but architecture does have an influence
on how people understand their God.
>> If you take the same religious practice
and you move it from
out of different buildings, you're going
to come up with a whole different type
of experience. So, the space itself
participates in
the religious experience of people.
>> Both megachurches and gothic cathedrals
make a clear statement to the members
and the larger community,
and that's nothing new.
The central purpose that unites all
sacred architecture is that the goal is
to communicate.
Every steeple, every stained glass
window, every parking lot is sending a
message to the membership and the larger
community.
David Johnson is about to communicate
with thousands of people over many
square miles.
But he won't be using any modern
technology.
To send this message, David will need to
climb high into a church tower.
Advancing toward a perch few people ever
experience.
The journey is not without certain
dangers.
David has made this trip many times
before.
>> Your heart, all your muscles, wonderful
exercise getting a workout just getting
up those 108 steps.
>> Now, high above the street,
David Johnson will play music
on church bells.
This musical device called a carillon, a
keyboard connected to dozens of bells to
create music.
>> But for all of its size, for all of that
bulk,
uh there's immense tenderness,
immense potential tenderness in a
carillon.
The possibility to play delicately, the
possibility to produce
all sorts of
suggestive, intricate sounds.
>> Bells have been a part of church
architecture for centuries.
In times past, church services were the
only weekly event that required everyone
to show up at a specific time and place.
And the best way to get a community in
sync
was to ring a bell.
The higher the bell was mounted, the
further the sound would travel.
In playing carillons around the country,
David Johnson has seen his share of very
high church towers. Some, he hopes never
to see again.
>> You get inside the piece of the building
that is a tower and literally climb
straight up a wall with
what amount to steps in a ladder.
I'd call it terrifying.
>> While bell towers can reach dizzying
heights, many are topped with an
architectural feature that reaches even
higher.
A steeple.
Why do so many churches have steeples?
Are they symbolically pointing the
faithful to God above?
Partly.
But, there is also another purpose.
>> The steeple
and the tower of the church actually
marks its presence in the midst of a
community.
Back in the day, when we didn't have
maps or maps weren't readily available,
you could identify the town
by the presence of the steeple.
>> If you're trying to make a statement and
you're trying to put yourself onto a
landscape within a urban environment or
wherever it might be, you're going to go
for height.
>> For many decades, the tallest steeple in
America was New York's St. Patrick's
Cathedral.
Towering above anything else in the city
in the era before skyscrapers.
>> St. Patrick's, the spires are 330
ft high. The at the time that they're
built, they're the tallest things other
than the Washington Monument uh in the
country.
That's tall.
>> No city exemplifies the competitive
quest for height more than Philadelphia
in the mid-1800s,
which was home to something of a steeple
arms race. Each congregation driving to
outdo the other.
>> They're saying, "We're here. We have the
tallest steeple. We are an important
congregation. You newcomers should be a
member of our church because of that."
>> To win the steeple war in Philadelphia,
10th Presbyterian Church hired the
architect known as the king of tall
steeples, John McArthur.
McArthur would later become famous for
designing the tallest building in the
country, City Hall in Philadelphia,
which held the title until it was
eclipsed by the Washington Monument.
McArthur's steeple masterpiece was built
to tower 248 ft above the street.
In an era before modern steel, it was
unclear how to best engineer a structure
25 stories high.
Building the steeple with stone would be
too expensive. So, McArthur settled on
timber, even though wood had not been
tested at such extreme heights.
In a 1912 windstorm, the steeple was
destroyed.
Only the base exists today.
It was a fate that was all too common in
the race for the tallest steeples in
America, as engineering had not yet
caught up with ambition.
>> It was a height war. You know, at some
point it was not going to work anymore.
>> So, there are many stories of many
churches in the earlier days where they
are going to build the biggest spire of
them all until they don't, and it comes
tumbling down.
>> In 1878, a single storm toppled over 50
church steeples along the eastern
seaboard.
While steeples are largely a Christian
design, domes have a much broader
history used for synagogues and mosques
as well.
All domes connect back to the Pantheon
in Rome, built in 126 AD.
It was a stupendous achievement,
measuring 142 ft across, half of a
football field. No one would build a
bigger dome
for 1,000 years.
The Pantheon was a religious building
dedicated to the Roman gods.
When Christianity became popular, many
Christian houses of worship continued
the tradition of including domes,
most famously, St. Peter's in Rome, home
of the Catholic Church.
>> It's really with the design of St.
Peter's in Rome back in
the early 1500s, all of a sudden you're
like, wait a minute. Now the dome, the
dome is the thing.
>> In America, the United States Capitol
Building was modeled on St. Peter's and
stood as the largest dome in the country
for decades.
But of course, the US Capitol is not a
church.
St. Josaphat is a church and its dome
was touted as second only to the Capitol
in size.
St. Josaphat was the brainchild of a
blacksmith turned priest named Wilhelm
Grutza, who wanted Milwaukee, Wisconsin
to have a replica of Rome's St. Peter's.
>> And then of course, for Catholics with
St. Peter being the most important
church in Catholicism,
why wouldn't you try to recreate that if
you could?
>> But how could Grutza make it affordable
enough to build? The stonework
especially would be prohibitively
expensive.
Early in the process, Grutza came up
with an ingenious cost-saving idea.
He bought the condemned post office in
downtown Chicago for pennies on the
dollar.
>> And they found out that a building was
going down in Chicago and they got the
stone on the on the cheap for that.
That's pretty good.
>> Grutza had the building moved piece by
piece more than 100 miles.
500 rail cars of stone were then
meticulously rearranged like a box of
Legos to build the church and dome.
The result was stunning.
But the constant fundraising took a toll
on Grutza.
In 1901,
with construction finally completed,
Grutza said the very first mass in the
church of his dreams
and then
promptly died.
The church stands today as a monument to
Grutza's vision and his congregation's
dedication.
More than 2,000 people can sit under the
dome to attend mass or enjoy a Christmas
concert.
But was this really the largest church
dome in America?
The people of Utah
would disagree.
In 1867,
Brigham Young had a problem.
As the leader of the Church of Jesus
Christ of Latter-day Saints, his church
membership was booming, but they
couldn't all fit under one roof.
Young's solution?
Build a bigger roof.
More specifically, he built a tabernacle
with a dome large enough that 15,000
people could worship together.
At first, no one was quite sure how to
build it.
>> Brigham Young, the head of the church,
had strong interest in architecture and
engineering. Um he had built bridges and
lots of buildings, and he was fascinated
with the structural systems.
>> Young got inspiration for the tabernacle
one morning at his breakfast. He stared
at a hard-boiled egg, then cut it
lengthwise, intuitively sensing he had
stumbled upon one of nature's strongest
shapes.
Young wondered how big the egg idea
could be scaled up.
His architect, Henry Grow, delivered the
answer.
A 150-ft
unsupported
span.
>> It's made with no nails because nails
were expensive. Um and so it's built
with wooden dowels. Those are wooden
nails that you hammer into wood, and
they expand when they're wet, and they
kind of fill the space, and held
strapped together with leather.
Um and uh the le- leather tightens when
it dries. So wet leather was put around
these structures and contracted and held
them together. It's a It's an
engineering marvel. It really is an
engineering marvel.
>> Perhaps the most amazing design feature
is the building's acoustics.
Built for sermons in an era before
electricity, the strength of a single
person's voice would need to be audible
to more than 10,000 people with no
microphones, no speakers.
Young was proud of his booming voice,
and Grow strategically positioned the
pulpit so that reflected sound would
carry.
Famously, a brass pin dropped in the
front of the church could be heard 200
ft away.
>> And the architecture is helping them.
The building, the shape of the roof, the
ceiling there with the curve is helping
and the curved seats there is helping
his voice project out um to the
audience.
>> Never before in history had such a large
crowd been able to hear a single
speaker.
But Brigham Young pulled it off thanks
to bold engineering
and a booming voice.
Gargoyles are surprisingly common on
American churches,
but they are up so high most people
never notice the odd creatures that look
like strange animals or demons.
>> Gargoyles are a way that masons have
fun. And many of them are funny-looking.
They're they they they don't look
serious.
>> Why have these beasts been so common in
church architecture?
Water is the enemy of church
foundations, so builders looked for ways
to throw water as far from the base of
the structure as possible.
Gargoyles are positioned at the end of a
water downspout and vomit water during a
significant downpour.
>> So, this is your tip. If you are ever by
a cathedral with gargoyles in a huge
rainstorm, get out of your house, go
over there cuz it's just shooting out.
It was amazing.
>> Gargoyles were such a popular element of
church architecture that builders began
adding these carvings in places without
downspouts, calling them grotesques.
For the stoneworkers who labored for
years on a project, gargoyles and
grotesques were an opportunity to be
creative.
>> And each time we're going to do it,
we're going to do it a little
differently cuz, you know, the guy that
did it before me, he's a hack. I'm going
to do mine like this. This Look at this.
This is like If you thought that was a
dragon, wait till you see this dragon.
Who needs dragons? I'm going to do mine
This is a guy spitting water right out
of its mouth. So, over and over again,
we reinterpret it.
>> One theme of most gargoyle design is to
represent hellish creatures who would
never set foot inside a church,
increasing the contrast between what was
seen as the ugly, corrupt world outside
the building and the beauty and
sanctuary inside.
>> I think they're scaring you. I think
they're always scaring you, right? To be
faithful, to not be wrong, to not do
wrong.
>> In America, most stone carvers' names
have been lost to history, but not all.
In fact, the artist who carved this
got his start carving gargoyles.
His name, Gutzon Borglum.
Long before Mount Rushmore, Borglum
toiled in relative obscurity as a
sculptor at St. John the Divine in New
York City.
But it was his work on the church's
angel sculptures that made national news
by igniting a scandal.
That's because Borglum's angels were
female.
Church leaders wanted only male angels
and wouldn't back down.
Borglum was so irate, he destroyed his
work. The tirade turned Gutzon Borglum
into a celebrity.
Most stone carvers weren't quite so
dramatic. In fact, there is a
centuries-long tradition of making
gargoyles that are designed to evoke a
laugh.
>> They're so interesting because that's
the moment where artisans really get to
do something fun.
>> And that explains the Darth Vader
gargoyle at the National Cathedral.
The church held a contest in 1986 and
invited ideas for a new gargoyle on the
north or dark side of the building. It's
no surprise that Darth Vader won.
Stained glass has been central to church
design since the Gothic era and even
before.
It stood as the most extraordinary art
available to common people in medieval
times, but the beauty of stained glass
isn't visible from outside.
Instead, townspeople had to enter the
church to experience the grandeur of
color and light.
In the United States, stained glass was
slow to catch on because early American
Protestants saw the art form as
frivolous, unnecessary.
>> Those Puritan groups, they didn't want
any of that
manipulated light. They wanted pure
white light coming in through their
windows.
>> As other denominations of Protestants
and Catholics immigrated to America,
interest in stained glass was renewed.
One reason is that the images in these
windows tell stories and reinforce
teachings that bond the community.
Even today, new stained glass
installations reflect the continuing
story of the church, like these windows
at Trinity in Chicago, a predominantly
African-American
congregation.
>> And you can stand there and study that
glass and learn a lot about the
African-American experience. They're
They're scenes.
You'll see Martin Luther King giving his
I Have a Dream speech, Harriet Tubman
bringing people through the Underground
Railroad.
>> Perhaps the most important stained glass
storyteller in America was Louis Comfort
Tiffany.
He was best known for his lamps, but
that was just a sideline. For most of
his career, his focus was church
windows.
Tiffany's workshop turned out thousands,
most still in place all across America.
>> We should recognize the fact that
Tiffany was a very smart businessman.
>> And as the business grew, Tiffany pushed
hard for innovation.
He developed a technique for stretching
and twisting glass. He mastered the
combination of different colors,
creating textures that mimic nature.
>> He studied chemistry and he really took
the opportunity to
experiment and so he was looking for new
techniques.
>> Tiffany hired a team of designers to
develop his windows. Among the more
noteworthy was Agnes Northrop, who
created nearly all Tiffany's landscape
motifs.
It was a major change in direction for
American stained glass, moving beyond
biblical scene to emphasize the
spiritual dimension of the natural
world.
>> And so suggesting a kind of beautiful,
peaceful scene. And so in that regard,
it's a different direction in glass, for
sure.
>> Northrup's landscapes added a sense of
perspective and three-dimensionality
that pushed boundaries.
>> So, you do have a sense in a landscape
that is a stream that the stream really
goes back into a further distant
landscape and that there's hills in the
back and that there's
um receding skies and that there the
trees get smaller as they get farther
away.
>> While Tiffany saw windows as a work of
art unto themselves, other designers
rejected this idea and imagined stained
glass as a servant to the larger church
design.
By transmitting patterns and colors of
light that were more important than the
image itself.
One ardent advocate for this view was an
artist named Charles Connick.
>> He said it, you know, the window
shouldn't be a picture. It should be
part of the architecture.
>> As a boy, Connick was bullied in school,
so he stayed inside at recess to avoid
the torment and spent his time coloring.
>> And then he also started to gain a lot
of respect from his classmates because
he would have all these wonderful
drawings on the chalkboard when they
came back from recess and uh they would
just, you know, marvel at how well they
could draw, so that was that was kind of
his, you know, first earned
self-respect.
>> As a young man, Connick visited the
Cathedral at Chartres in France, home to
some of the most impressive stained
glass of the Middle Ages.
There, he had an epiphany as he realized
the real artistry of stained glass is
the projection of fine-tuned colors
combining like a musical score.
>> How light penetrates the outside into
the inside, makes a difference in how
the building comes alive to the people
inside of it.
And so, all through the day
the light changes.
And the quality of the space changes
with the light.
>> Connick's focus on color can be easily
seen at one of his masterpieces, House
of Hope in St. Paul, Minnesota.
Here, the light is always changing
throughout the day and across the
seasons,
all carefully tuned to create an
environment of beauty
and wonder.
>> When clouds move, there's animation in
our glass.
And we are physical beings
that need light in order to change our
mood.
>> The changing beauty and emotional impact
of stained glass is the reason this art
form endured as a fundamental element of
church design. The mosaic colors of
Connick to the intricate landscapes of
Tiffany and the artistic contributions
of dozens of other artisans all
contribute to an art form that's seen by
more people every week than all the
world's museum exhibits combined.
Christian churches fall into three main
categories:
Catholic, Protestant,
and Orthodox.
Once inside, all three types have a
surprising number of similarities
despite looking wildly dissimilar.
In the front, most Christian churches
have a prominent pulpit where sermons
are delivered.
Over time, pulpits have been used less
and less
as sermons are often delivered closer to
the membership.
>> The necessity of being
elevated
becomes less important
than being able to move freely so that I
can project side to side and move closer
to people
that I'm
uh and trying to engage in whatever
message I'm presenting.
>> If we don't make up in our mind in 2014
>> For Protestants, this connection is
especially clear in churches with a
large African-American membership where
the preaching reflects a dialogue
between pastor and congregation.
>> It is a dialogue. It's a conversation.
You know, the the pastor or the preacher
is saying what they're saying and then
the the congregation is responding to
that and it is in real time.
So, because of that, you're not going to
have a lot of distance between people.
Cuz he needs to see me go.
Right? We're on the same page, you know,
uh so people are going to be closer
together.
>> Catholic churches are likely to include
statues of biblical figures or later
saints.
Orthodox churches have their own unique
images and art, often called
iconography.
Protestants run the full range from the
highly decorated to the extremely
spartan.
The latter reflecting a strain of
American Protestantism that dates to the
Pilgrims and Puritans who first settled
in New England.
Superficially
Jewish synagogues might seem similar to
Christian churches. It's common for a
synagogue to have pews for seating and
similar artistic expressions.
Both Jewish and Christian houses of
worship have seating,
but Muslim mosques do not.
Mosques do house a weekly gathering
which includes prayers and a sermon,
typically delivered from a raised
platform.
This historic church is setting up for
its biggest day of the year.
On the Christian calendar, Easter is the
most important holiday, but it's
Christmas that attracts the largest
crowds. And one key reason
is music.
Most American churches are designed with
music in mind. Some feature domes, which
have acoustic properties to enhance the
sound.
Typically, there is special seating for
a choir. Sometimes in the back of the
church, but in the past century, many
choirs have been moved to the front.
Next to the choir's location is
typically the home of the most popular
church instrument,
the pipe organ.
>> We don't typically think of the pipe
organ as technology,
but in fact, that technology was brought
in to enhance the worship.
>> Prior to the Industrial Revolution, pipe
organs were the most complicated
mechanical devices built by humans.
Yet, even modest churches in America are
likely to have an organ.
How could they afford it?
Part of the reason is this.
Steel mills made Andrew Carnegie
enormously rich.
A church-going Presbyterian, he used
some of that money to fund church pipe
organs, nearly 8,000 around the country.
Many churches have switched to more
contemporary musical instruments.
The advent of modern music in church has
created an architectural challenge.
Space needs to be reconfigured for
drums, electronic equipment, and
featured singers.
>> Praise band, very different experience,
and very different acoustic required
for contemporary praise band experience
and worship than for
more traditional sacred music.
>> In many churches, the area in the front
that formerly was reserved for specific
activities has now morphed into a blank
slate platform that can be adapted for a
range of uses.
>> There's just a lot that you can do with
lighting to evoke a certain kind of
emotion. So, I think that if um if
there's one element in the church that
um in our church architecture that you
can use to
create theater,
it would be lighting.
>> This creates something of a curious
juxtaposition in architecture, with the
inside of the church reflecting the
latest in modern music, technology, and
graphics, while the outside often echoes
traditions from a thousand years before.
But that should not be a surprise.
American religion has always bridged two
worlds.
Every house of worship has dual roles to
engage the community as it exists today
and to maintain a connection to ancient
truths.
It's not easy to pull off,
but the quest is visible every day,
reflected in sacred architecture
across the country.
>> This is the most important building for
most everyone.
>> You're entering into something that's
unique and special. It this building is
different from anything else.
>> In architecture, when it's well done,
you are never far from someone
delivering a message.
>> What's important is that you you're
inspired.
And that you are you're seeing things
that inspire you um and uh remind you
that uh you're a child of God.
>> So every faith, no matter what it is,
finds a way to take their beliefs and
manifest them in built form. And that's
an incredibly powerful thing.
>> While great architecture is beautiful,
these buildings were not designed to be
toured like museums.
Their purpose is to serve as a gathering
place for people.
>> The church, which isn't just a building,
it's the people that occupy the
building. That's the church.
>> Mhm.